Guide to the Fagel Stern Papers TAM.091
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fagel Stern Papers
1922-1983
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stern, Fagel, 1904-1936
Stern, Phyllis
TAM.091
0.25 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
Faygle Stern (circa 1904-1936) was a Polish Jewish communist active in the Jewish Section of the International Workers Order in New York. She came to the United States in 1921, and died in childbirth in January, 1936. The collection includes her diary, correspondence with her brother Abram Judah, a communist who lived in Havana and the USSR, and biographical material (reminiscence, sketch, obituary). The diary, notebooks, and most of the letters are in Yiddish.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Phyllis Stern (niece of Fagel Stern), 1990. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1990.005 and 1990.008.
Historical/Biographical Note
Faygle Stern (circa 1904-1936), was a Jewish communist active in the Jewish Section of the International Workers Order, primarily as a teacher in the Yiddish shule movement in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn, New York. She was born in Ostroleka (a.k.a. Ostrolenka), Poland, came to the United States in 1921, and died in childbirth in January, 1936.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains Stern's diary; two notebooks with comments on Jews, Zionism, and world affairs; correspondence from family members, friends, and colleagues; and photographs. The collection also contains biographical material.
Existence and Location of Copies
Box 1 of this collection are photocopies of the original materials in Box 2.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author.
The files are grouped into two series:
Series I: Papers
Series II: Photographs
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the access photocopies in Box 1.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Jewish teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jews, Polish |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jewish communists |z Cuba.; Zionism.; Political activists |z New York (State) |z Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Jewish communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Diaries; International Workers Order. Jewish Section; Stern, Phyllis
- Series I: Papers, 1922-1983
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains Stern's diary, maintained during her fatal pregnancy, in which personal and political concerns are co-mingled. The series also contains her political notebooks; letters from her brother Abram Judah, also a communist who lived in Havana before returning to the USSR, where he died in 1933; letters from her brother Beryl, who came to the U.S. from Ostrolenka in 1935, and letters from her brother Chiel, who remained in Poland. The collection also contains biographical material on Stern including a reminiscence, sketch, and obituary.
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) - Death., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) - letters from Cuba to Fagel Stern, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) and Fagel Stern - Immigration to United States - Documents., 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stern, Beryl - letters to Fagel Stern., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stern, Beryl - letter from R.Saltzman, National Secretary, Jewish Section, International Workers Order., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stern, Chiel - letters to Fagel and Beryl Stern., 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stern, Fagel - Biographical materials., 1936-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stern, Fagel - Diary., Jul 1935-Jan 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stern, Fagel - letters to Abram and Beryl Stern., 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stern, Fagel - Political notebooks., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stern, Naftali (uncle of Fagel) - letter to Fagel Stern., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tante - letter to Fagel Stern., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Photographs, circa 1924 (Box 2)
  This series contains four items, including two black-and-white prints and two letters. Both photographs include Fagel Stern, dated 1924. Both letters are addressed to Phyllis Stern.